Guide to the Alfred Stieglitz / Georgia O'Keeffe Archive
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Many letters from grade school and college friends, as well as former neighbors in Wisconsin and Virginia, can be found in this subseries. Several of these individuals were prompted to send accounts of their memories of O'Keeffe by a subsequent event connected with the painter, such as the 1977 WNET documentary, or coverage of a one-woman exhibition. Most of these letters are single letters, and are filed in the alphabetic general folders, along with similar writings from people who had relationships with her, or Stieglitz, from the 291 period. For example, Alice Holtman, the former secretary at An American Place, kept in contact, as did old friends "Mike" Harding and "Wick" Moore. Letters from unidentified writers are filed at the end of the alphabetical arrangement; letters from "Gus", an unidentified admirer who refers to their past relationship, are foldered separately.
A subseries of Subject Files preserves the filing order from O'Keeffe's home. Folders of correspondence and treatment reports from conservators who worked on her paintings, either for O'Keeffe or institutions, are followed by random biographical writings and material prepared for publication. Like essays can be found in the correspondence subseries as well, but those found in Box 222 were isolated when the files came to the library. A small group of material related to Alfred Stieglitz follows, containing a file of condolence notes written to O'Keeffe upon his death.
A sizable portion of the correspondence in Series I, however, came to O'Keeffe from people who were admirers, students, former friends (from Wisconsin and Virginia), people who claimed to own paintings of hers, and even non-related O'Keeffes who were hoping to find a family connection. The subseries of Fan Mail remains much as it was received by the library, but the files were combed for letters from anyone who had a direct personal relationship with the painter (as distinct from letters from people who only knew of O'Keeffe from seeing her work in a museum or publication) and those more substantive letters moved to the first subseries of correspondence. Fans in this section include museum security guards, a former elevator operator at the Sheldon, many art students, and even a mounted policeman from New York City. They asked O'Keeffe for autographs, opinions on their own work, advice on moving to New Mexico, and actual oil paintings. In exchange, and hoping to bond with her, they sent rocks, photographs of themselves and their families, and snapshots of their own works of painting and sculpture. From notes made on the incoming letters, it appears that O'Keeffe responded to a remarkable number of these writers. A few fan letters were removed to the correspondence subseries because of their special contents. Salvatore Bacigalufo, an Italian self-described "master of supertankers" working for Texaco, would visit museums while on layovers in port cities, and sent O'Keeffe his modern-day versions of the traditional sailors' valentines made of pressed flowers. Lorraine Bubar held annual O'Keeffe birthday celebrations at her home, and sent photographs of O'Keeffe-inspired cakes, decorations, and partygoers. Groups of paintings, drawings, essays, and poems sent to her by school children were also removed and filed with correspondence in the first subseries.
The contents of Boxes 223-233 are filed by year, and are in no order within each year, as are those of box 234, Rights and Reproductions Correspondence, which deals with requests to reproduce, borrow, or lend O'Keeffe works, as well as requests for donations of paintings, posters, and books and permission to make documentary films about her. Further rights and reproductions letters appear in the first subseries, in the files of museums which held her work, notably the Metropolitan and Philadelphia museums of art.
Series IX. Georgia O'Keeffe: Documentary Ephemera, (Boxes 235-237), contains Clipping Files, a small selection of invitations filed as Exhibition Ephemera, and Miscellaneous Ephemera found among her correspondence files. Clipping Files document O'Keeffe's life, work, and exhibitions, and include articles on people and topics of interest to her. The files include clippings kept by Stieglitz (some of which have citations and dates in his hand), which were merged with those received with O'Keeffe's papers in 1992.
Series X. Georgia O'Keeffe: Awards and Medals, (Boxes 238-240), contains diplomas, certificates, and medals awarded to O'Keeffe during her lifetime, as well as photographs documenting the ceremonies. They include a number of honorary degrees from prominent universities and colleges, awards bestowed by the Governors of her home and adopted states, and one of the country's highest honors, the Presidential Medal of Freedom. The series is arranged in alphabetical order by the institution or organization giving the award.
Stieglitz Family Papers (Series XI)
Stieglitz Family Papers (Series XI), (Boxes 241-245), is arranged into two subseries: Edward and Hedwig Stieglitz Papers; and Other Family Papers. The first and largest subseries consists mainly of the personal correspondence of Alfred Stieglitz's parents, Edward and Hedwig Stieglitz, with a few business-related letters interspersed. Many of the letters in this series are written in Deutscher schrift (Sütterlin), and a few in Yiddish. Translations were made for several randomly selected family letters before the series was given to the library; these have been interfiled with the originals. The Family Correspondence includes a number of letters written to Edward Stieglitz from his brothers during his Civil War service, and added on to by other family members and friends (see also a file of "Group letters" at the end of the section). It also contains a significant set of reports sent almost daily from Hedwig to her husband while he was away from home on two summer trips, one in 1872 when he and eight-year-old Alfred went to take the waters at Sharon Springs, New York, and then to see Niagara Falls, and a second journey the two made a year later to the great tourist hotels in the White Mountains of New Hampshire, and Lake George, Saratoga Springs and the Catskill Mountains in New York State. These letters to Edward and Alfred were family efforts, jointly written by Hedwig and her two sisters Rosa and Ida, with additional notes added by the Stieglitz children. Also prominent in Hedwig's letters to her husband are those from her 1889 trip to Los Angeles to await the birth of their first grandchild; the subsequent and tragic death of their daughter Flora, following the delivery of her stillborn baby, is recorded in a series of letters and telegraphed reports as her body was brought home to New York for burial.
The files of Personal and Business Correspondence contain letters from family friends as well as Edward Stieglitz's business partner Hermann Hahlo and other colleagues. Hahlo's letters include financial statements of their company's business dealings during the years that Stieglitz served in the army and was traveling overseas. The artists Fedor Encke and Moses Ezekiel were regular correspondents. Ezekiel, an American sculptor, lived and worked in Italy. In a series of letters from 1879 and 1880, he describes his life there and includes snapshot photographs of local scenery and the interior of his studio.
Personal Papers contains an assortment of ephemeral items such as invoices made by Alfred Stieglitz of money owed him by his father in 1873 and 1874, and business and calling cards; among the latter group is Hedwig Werner and Edward Stieglitz's Velobungskarten, a special calling card which marked their engagement. A file of printed ephemera contains curiosities such as a ship passenger track chart for an 1881 Atlantic crossing, a label for wine imported by Stieglitz and a 19th-century facsimile of the April 15, 1865, New York Evening Express which carries news of Abraham Lincoln's assassination. A few miscellaneous documents from Stieglitz's army days are foldered together, among them a receipt from the substitute he paid to fulfill his service requirement. Also filed here is an accounting of Levi Stieglitz's estate and a variety of records for the Stieglitz's household and personal expenses, including a detailed invoice for furnishings purchased in 1872 for their new home on East 60th Street in New York.
The section entitled Drawings consists of a small collection of works by Edward Stieglitz, most drawn after the paintings of Wilhelm Hasemann, a noted German artist and family friend. Hasemann's own work is well represented in a fine album containing a series of careful pencil drawings of German landscapes and local residents, which he made on standard-issue postal cards. Mailed to the Stieglitz family over a period of three years, 1882-85, each is signed and dated, and many are inscribed with notes and news from the artist as well as any Stieglitz family members with him at the time. A third artist whose drawing can be found here is Anton Brioschi, a Viennese painter known for his work in scenery for the theater, opera, and ballet.
The second subseries, Other Family Papers, contains two folders of letters written by the paternal and maternal grandfathers of Alfred Stieglitz: one from Levi Stieglitz to his daughter Pauline; and one from Abraham Werner to his wife Flora.
Appendix One: Notes on the contents of Stieglitz Scrapbooks (Series III. Boxes 102-109)
Scrapbook Number 1: 1900-12, n.d.
Contains material concerning the Photo-Secession exhibition at Buffalo (Albright Art Gallery, 1910); copies of Photo-Secession and Its Opponents: Five Recent Letters and Photo-Secession and Its Opponents: Another Letter - The Sixth (1910); reviews of "291" exhibitions of Rousseau (1910), Cezanne, Picasso, Burgess, and de Meyer (all 1911), Hartley, Dove, Matisse, children's art, Frueh and Walkowitz (all 1912); review of Paris exhibition (1900) and sse, children's Artists (1910) and of exhibitions of Pamela C. Smith (Berlin Photographic, 1912), Weber (Murray Hill, 1912), Davidson (Glaenzer, 1912), Sterne (Berlin Photographic, 1912); articles on Stieglitz by Laurvik (1911), Hapgood (1912) and on Camera Work No. 36 and the Stein special issue (1912); articles on Shaw (1909), Post-Impressionism (1911), Professional Photographers' Society meeting (1912), Pamela C. Smith (n.d.), women photographers (n.d.); list of honorary fellows of the Royal Photographic Society (1912); Stieglitz images removed from publications (1900, 1902); one issue of The Black Mirror (1912). 202 pages.
Scrapbook Number 2: 1902-11
Contains: prospectus, renewal form, distribution announcement, reviews and correspondence relating to Camera Work (1902-04); reviews of Photo-Secession (1907) and "291" exhibitions of Rodin, Higgins, Toulouse-Lautrec, Matisse, and de Zayas (1907-10); announcement for Weber exhibition signed by Scott and Kennerley (1911); catalogues for Steichen exhibitions at Glaenzer (1905) and Montross (1910) galleries; catalogue of Wiener Photoklub exhibition (1910); entry form and review of Dresden exhibition (1909); clippings on Camera Club of New York controversy (1908); Stieglitz letter to editor about Roosevelt (1910). 198 pages.
Scrapbook Number 3: 1902-13, n.d.
Contains: letter from Roversi (Turin exhibition, 1902); exhibition catalogues and reviews of Photo-Secession show at National Arts Club (1902); exhibition catalogues for salons which included Photo-Secession loans held in 1903 at Toronto, Cleveland, Minneapolis, Denver, and Rochester; reviews of Photo-Secession show at Corcoran Gallery of Art (1904) and Carnegie Institute (1904); review of exhibitions in Vienna (1904-05) and Dresden (1904); articles on the Louisiana Purchase Exposition (1903-04); article on Stieglitz by Muir (1913), on Photo-Secession (1902-03) and de Zayas (1910); several articles by Hartmann (1904); Stieglitz images removed from publications ([Kitty at Christmas tree], n.d., "The Steerage" on a Saturday Evening Mail cover, 1912). 97 pages.
Scrapbook Number 4: 1896-1907
Contains: Photo-Secession records including prospectus mailed to members, list of members and announcement of gallery opening, checklist and reviews of first members' exhibition (all 1905); exhibition announcements, checklists and reviews of "291" exhibitions for seasons 1905-06 and 1906-07; placards from "291" street signboard for Kasebier/White (1906), Seeley, Rodin, and Steichen exhibitions (all 1908); press release on the Steichen/Eugene/Stieglitz color photography exhibition (1907); articles on Photo-Secession by Poore (1905), Rood (1905), Conway (1906), Savery (n.d.) and others unsigned; exhibition announcements, catalogues and reviews for Photo-Secession shows at Cincinnati Museum (1906), Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts (1906) and School of Ethical Culture, New York (1907); catalogue of Stieglitz lantern slides (1896). 98 pages.
Scrapbook Number 5: 1897-1916, n.d.
Contains: telegram from St. Petersburg (1903) and letter from Munsey's Magazine (1906); articles by Stieglitz on the Photo-Secession (1903) and the Louisiana Purchase Exposition (1904); articles on Stieglitz by Bayley (1904), Keiley (1904), Ernst (1908), Hapgood (1912), Muir (1913), du Bois (1915), Traubel (1916), Barnes (1917) and on "291" by G.B. [Guido Bruno?] (1918); articles on Camera Club controversy (1908); review of Photo-Secession exhibitions at Carnegie Institute (1904), Corcoran Gallery of Art (1904), Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts (1906) and Dresden (1909); review of "291" exhibitions of Photo-Secession members (1906-07), Rodin, Seeley, Smith/Geiger/MacLaughlan, Steichen and Matisse (all 1908), Steichen, Laurvik/de Zayas, Hartley, Japanese prints (all 1909); review of exhibition at National Arts Club (1908), of Steichen exhibition (Glaenzer, 1908) and the Forum Exhibition (1916); clipping of de Zayas cariactures of "Black Hand Fakirs'" ball (1909); articles on Camera Work (1903-15), 291 (1915), the Photo-Secession (1903-05), Turin exhibition (1902), Chicago salon (1904), autochromes (1907), Herzog (1907); articles on photography by Hartmann (1904-05), Laurvik (1908), Hoeber (1909), Hughes (n.d.), Rood (n.d.) and Edgerton (n.d.); on color photography by Laurvik (1908), on the Photo-Secession by Hartmann (1904) and Oliver (1905?), on the Linked Ring (1909); Emmy Stieglitz's copy of menu from "A Post-Impression" dinner (1913); award announcement/catalogue of Bausch & Lomb competition (1903); full issue of Camera Club of New York Journal (1897). 205 pages.
Scrapbook Number 6: 1887-1909, n.d.
Contains: correspondence, clippings and reviews regarding competitions, prizes and awards won by Stieglitz (1887-1900); citation issued by Camera Club of New York for his work on Camera Notes (1898), issues of their Journal (1896), and articles on Camera Notes (1901-02); article on Camera Work (1904); membership certificate from Hamburg amateur photographers club (1900); published articles by Stieglitz on cold bath platinotypes (1891), color slides (1892), slide plates (1892), Philadelphia salon (1893), pictorial photography (1895-99), the hand camera (1897), lantern slides (1897), night photography (1898), the Chassagne-Dansac process (1898), outdoor photography (1898), a favorite picture (n.d.), use of color screen (n.d.), uranium toning of platinotypes (n.d.), and "Twelve Random Don'ts" (1909); articles on Stieglitz by Hughes (1897), Hartmann (1898, 1900) and Dreiser (1899); general articles on photography (1890s) and a visit from Kasebier to White (1902); catalogues, invitations and reviews of Stieglitz show at the Camera Club of New York (1899) and showings of his lantern slides (1896-97); prospectus for Picturesque Bits of New York; invitation, catalogue, reviews and installation photograph of Photo-Secession show at National Arts Club (1902); exhibition catalogues for Camera Club of Hartford (1891), Society of Amateur Photographers (1893), Timmins Collection (1896), Camera Club of New York (Lantern Slides, 1897), Royal Photographic Society (1900), Turin exhibition (1902), Toronto Camera Club (1903), International Exhibition of Pictorial Photography (New York, 1909); reviews of above exhibitions plus Society of Amateur Photographers (1891), Kodak exhibition (1898), Florence exhibition (1899), Philadelphia salon (1900), Chicago salon (1900), Wiener Photoklub (1904), London salon (1908); catalogue of Steichen exhibition at La Maison des Artistes (Paris, 1902); specimen sheet for The Photochrome Engraving Company (1893); Stieglitz images (collotypes and halftones, etc.) removed from foreign and American publications (1887-1900) including photogravures of a Berlin exhibit (1889), "Weary" (1890), "A Happy New Year" (1895), "Hour of Prayer" (1895) and "Going to Prayers" [also known as "Scurrying Home"], "On the Dykes" (1895), "Mushrooms by the Sea (1896), "Watching for the Return" (1899). 200 pages.
Scrapbook Number 7: 1877-88
Contains: cast lists cut from programs of operas, concerts, plays, and other performances attended by Stieglitz primarily in New York and Berlin, but including events at Lake George, Karlsruhe, Munich, Bayreuth, Heidelberg, Weimar, Bremen, Liepzig, Baden-Baden, Dresden, Hamburg, Nurnberg, Stuttgart, Milan, Venice, Parma, Vienna, Salzburg, Interlaken, Bern, Lucerne and Budapest. Most of the programs are from operas, and the volume includes two handwritten alphabetical lists on the first few pages: one giving the title of each opera with an abbreviated cast list, and a second short list of all the operas seen (though these do not serve as an index because the volume in unpaginated). The book also includes programs for non-theatrical events such as a debate between the Eucleian (New York University) and Clionian (City College of New York) clubs (1880), the fall athletic games at City College (1880), exercises at the New York Riding Club (1881), concerts held by the New York Philharmonic Club (1880-81), circus performances in Berlin, and school festivals at Karlsruhe. Pasted in, on the inside of the front and back covers, are portraits of Edwin Booth and an unidentified woman, cut from serials. Approximately 200 pages.
Scrapbook Number 8: 1888-1902
Contains: cast lists cut from programs of plays, concerts, recitals, operas, comedies, vaudeville and music hall performances attended by Stieglitz, primarily in New York and Berlin, but including events in Washington, Bayreuth, Munich, Oberammergau, Vienna, Paris, Biarritz, Bordeaux and London. Most of the programs are from theatrical performances. The volume includes a handwritten index at the back, arranged alphabetically by title of the work performed, with an abbreviated cast list and the page number to find the program. The book also includes programs for circus performances, one exhibition of trained animal acts (1894), a benefit concert and ball for Mount Sinai nursing school (1891), and an entertainment by the Alpha Delta Phi Dramatic Association (1891). Also pasted in are an invitation, menu and newspaper announcement for the Stieglitz/Obermeyer wedding (1893) and a newspaper clipping on the wedding of Agnes Foord (1892), as well as a portrait of Adelina Patti on the inside of the front cover. 232 pages.
Boxed with the scrapbook is a file holding programs and tearsheets which were laying together loose in the front and back of the book.
Appendix Two: Clipping Boards (Series III. Boxes 115-116)
The subseries consists of entire newspaper pages, and some clipped articles, which have been dry mounted to sheets of acidic (and now fragile) pulpboard. Many of the sheets have pieces mounted on both sides. The papers include New York, Boston, Springfield and other dailies, with just a few articles cut from magazines and periodicals. Most of the articles concern Stieglitz and artists in his circle, and cover exhibitions of their work at museums and at his galleries. Authors are listed if a byline appeared or if Stieglitz annotated the article with an attribution. The following list gives the Stieglitz-related articles on each page of the newspaper that appears on each board. Readers should first check the clipping files in Series III to see if an article of interest appears there before using these fragile clipping boards.
In Portfolio One:
Sheet 1: Hapgood on the Armory Show (1913 Feb 17); Hapgood on Stieglitz photographs (1913 Mar 8)
Sheet 2: Article on Steichen mural commission, Paris (1911 Sep 24); Picabia on New York (1913)
Sheet 3: Caffin on Walkowitz (1913 Nov); Laurvik on Cezanne and Picasso (1913 Apr 12)
Sheet 4: Caffin on "291" (1914 Mar); Kreymborg on Stieglitz (1914 Jun 14)
Sheet 5: On "291" (1925); Caffin on "291" (1914); Chamberlin on value (1919 Jan 22); on Marin (1931 Dec 27)
Sheet 6: On the Armory Show (1913 Mar 2); Cox on Cubists and Futurists (1913 Mar 16)
Sheet 7: Caffin on Marin (1913 Jan 27); Wedell on Stieglitz (1913 Mar 16)
Sheet 8: On Picabia (1913 Mar 9); Tyrrell on Marin (1921 Apr 18)
Sheet 9: On the Armory Show (1913 Feb 18); Jewell on Demuth and O'Keeffe (1929 Feb 24)
Sheet 10: Freed on Stieglitz (1924 Jan 18); Watson on Nadelman (1917 Feb 3)
Sheet 11: Cortissoz on post-Impressionism (1913 Feb 23); Ernst on Stieglitz (1908)
Sheet 12: On the Armory Show (1913 Feb 25); on O'Keeffe paintings purchased by Metropolitan Museum (1934 Mar 26)
Sheet 13: On the Armory Show (1913 Mar 10); Seligmann on Stieglitz (1921 Feb 16)
Sheet 14 Picabia on Futurism (1913 Apr 13); Matthias on O'Keeffe (1926 Mar 2)
Sheet 15: Tyrrell on Stieglitz (1917 Sep 28); McCausland on Stieglitz (1933 May 14)
Sheet 16: Stieglitz on Paris exhibition (1919 Apr 6)
Sheet 17: Caffin on Marin (1915 Feb 22); Frank on Stieglitz (1925 Mar 14) Sheet 18: Caffin on Steichen (1915 Feb 1)
Sheet 19: On Marin (1920 Apr 12); on O'Keeffe (1933 Dec 10)
Sheet 20: On Picabia (1913 Mar 18); Stevenson on Stieglitz (1927 May 6)
Sheet 21: Marin on architecture (1913 Feb 16); on children's painting (1912 Apr 27)
Sheet 22: Caffin on Armory Show (1913 Feb); Jewell on Stieglitz (1934 Dec 16)
Sheet 23: On the Armory Show (1913 Feb 17); Seligmann on Stieglitz collection at Metropolitan Museum and on Strand (1929 Mar 23)
Sheet 24: Caffin on Picasso (1914 Dec 14); Stieglitz on modern art (1913 Jan 26)
Sheet 25: On Picasso and pre-Columbian art (1914 Dec 20); on O'Keeffe (1929 Feb 10)
In Portfolio Two:
Sheet 26: Caffin on Coburn's history of photography exhibition (1914 Dec 7); McCausland on Stieglitz and Marin (1931 Oct 24)
Sheet 27: On Hartley (1933 Oct 28)
Sheet 28: McBride on Hartley (1936 Mar 28)
Sheet 29: McCausland on O'Keeffe (1934 Feb 18); Fort on Stieglitz (1927 May 18)
Sheet 30: McBride on Walkowitz (1916 Dec 31); McBride on Picabia (1913 Mar 18); Tyrrell on O'Keeffe (1916 Jun 2)
Sheet 31: Cortissoz on Marin (1936 Oct 25)
Sheet 32: Eishelmius letter to McBride (1936 Nov 7)
Sheet 33: Tyrrell on O'Keeffe (1917 May 4); Stieglitz suggested for committee on standardization of art (1915 Jun 18)
Sheet 34: Nesbit Chapter III (n.d.)
Sheet 35: Liffmann on photographers (1930 Apr 4)
Sheet 36: Frank on Stieglitz (1927 May)
Sheet 37: Hapgood on Stein (1912 Sep 25); Tyrrell on Engelhard (1916 Dec 8); Laurvik on Marin (1913 Jan 25)
Sheet 38: Hapgood on Marin (1913 Jan 27); on Marin (n.d.); on Camera Club Controversy (1908 Feb 15)
Sheet 39: Cortissoz on O'Keeffe (1929 Feb 10); on Rhoades/Beckett (1915 Feb 1)
Sheet 40: McBride on O'Keeffe (1934 Feb 3); on Marin (1925 Dec 20)
Sheet 41: Huneker on Matisse (1908 Apr 10); McCausland on O'Keeffe (1932 Jan 10)
Sheet 42: Hapgood on Daniels (1912 Mar 16); on the Forum exhibition (1916 Mar 25)
Sheet 43: Hapgood on Weber on Stein (1913 Mar 21)
Sheet 44: McBride on Marin (1936 Oct 24)
Sheet 45: Dust jacket for America and Alfred Stieglitz (1935)
Sheet 46: McCausland on Stieglitz (1934 Dec 2)
Sheet 47: Sherburne on O'Keeffe (1935 Feb 2)